<?xml-stylesheet href="/rss.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Li Chen's blog</title><link>https://aspcompiler.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Li Chen's blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2023 Li Chen</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2023 22:16:35 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aspcompiler.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Remaking of My Blog with Hugo</title><link>https://aspcompiler.github.io/posts/remaking-of-my-blog/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2023 22:16:35 -0800</pubDate><guid>https://aspcompiler.github.io/posts/remaking-of-my-blog/</guid><description>Li Chen's blog https://aspcompiler.github.io/posts/remaking-of-my-blog/ -&lt;h1 id="the-remaking">The remaking&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I have not blogged since I joined Amazon in 2016. My initial focus was &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.jobs/content/en/our-workplace/leadership-principles">delivery results&lt;/a> and then I had to deal with a massive volume of customer interactions and data as the result. Now I want to blog again as I spend significant time doing R&amp;amp;D at AWS Center for Quantum Computing and I need to capture what I learnt, and hopefully that benefits others as well. My original blog site was developed on &lt;a href="https://docs.github.com/en/pages/setting-up-a-github-pages-site-with-jekyll">github pages using Jekyll&lt;/a>. The Jekyll has changed significantly so that the side will not build.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="the-first-attempt-updating-jekyll">The first attempt: updating Jekyll&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Updating Jekyll has not been a smooth ride. Jekyll is developed in &lt;a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby&lt;/a>. The latest version of Ruby is currently 3.2 but github pages is only compatible with 3.1.3. So one actually has to start with a Ruby version manager such as &lt;a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/installation/macos/">chruby&lt;/a> to have multiple versions of Ruby in a system. Then one has to install Ruby Gems into per project environment using &lt;a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/ruby-101/">bundler&lt;/a>. Then once every few months, I need to update my Gems and ensure that they are compatible with each other. That is a bit too much maintenance if I just need a tool to write a blog.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="trying-hugo">Trying Hugo&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo&lt;/a> is another popular static site generator written in &lt;a href="https://go.dev/">Go&lt;/a>. Hugo developers have resolved all dependency conflicts at build time to make it a single executable so that the installation is extremely easy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hugo deploys hugo modules as git submodules so &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/">git&lt;/a> is required. This is a bit harsh for non-software-developers but OK for me. Using git submodules for distributing/versioning dependencies definitely is not as easy as versioned packages. However, I have only one submodule which is my &lt;a href="https://github.com/AmazingRise/hugo-theme-diary">Dairy theme&lt;/a> which has more features than I currently need. Let us see how it goes.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="getting-started">Getting Started&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The installation is very straight-forward. Just follow the &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/categories/installation/">instructions for each platform&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Then one can just follow &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/getting-started/quick-start/">quick start&lt;/a>. When I get to the step of adding &lt;code>ananke&lt;/code> theme, I jumped to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/AmazingRise/hugo-theme-diary#quick-start">Dairy instructions&lt;/a> instead.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="configuration">Configuration&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Most of the configurations are in the &lt;code>config.toml&lt;/code> file. One first needs to follow the instructions to set &lt;code>baseUrl&lt;/code>, &lt;code>title&lt;/code>, &lt;code>theme&lt;/code>, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="configuring-main-menu">Configuring Main Menu&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Configuring the main menu is pretty straightforward. Just add several &lt;code>[[menu.main]]&lt;/code> elements. The double square-bracket means array in toml.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>[[menu.main]]
url = &amp;#34;/about&amp;#34;
name = &amp;#34;About&amp;#34;
weight = 1
[[menu.main]]
url = &amp;#34;/posts&amp;#34;
name = &amp;#34;Posts&amp;#34;
weight = 2
[[menu.main]]
url = &amp;#34;/index.xml&amp;#34;
name = &amp;#34;RSS Feed&amp;#34;
weight = 3
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Hugo recognizes some of the urls like &lt;code>posts&lt;/code> and &lt;code>index.xml&lt;/code> out of the box while we have to add contents for &lt;code>about&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="comments">Comments&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Hugo supports several comment systems from free to paid. One of the easiest free ones is &lt;a href="https://utteranc.es/">utterance&lt;/a> which uses github issues to store comments. The configuration for utterance is:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>[params.utterances]
repo=&amp;#34;aspcompiler/aspcompiler.github.io&amp;#34;
theme=&amp;#34;github-light&amp;#34;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;h2 id="search">Search&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>One of the easiest ways to get search functionality is to configure &lt;a href="https://github.com/AmazingRise/hugo-theme-diary/wiki/Customization#add-google-search-box-on-your-site">google search&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="syntax-highlighter">Syntax Highlighter&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Dairy theme has a default &lt;a href="https://github.com/AmazingRise/hugo-theme-diary/wiki/Customization#about-highlight">code highlighter&lt;/a> and we will see how it goes.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="cicd">CI/CD&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To deploy to &lt;code>site.github.io&lt;/code>, one has to configure github action to build the site. This is basically adding and config the page &lt;code>.github/workflows/gh-pages.yml&lt;/code>. Follow the &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/hosting-and-deployment/hosting-on-github/">instructions&lt;/a> from Hugo.&lt;/p>
- https://aspcompiler.github.io/posts/remaking-of-my-blog/ - 2023 Li Chen</description></item></channel></rss>